Inventory of the William P. Wreden collection
Hoover Institution Archives
William P. Wreden collection
1914-1918
XX280
Hoover Institution Archives
6 manuscript boxes (2.4 linear feet)
Scrapbooks of newspaper clippings from the British press and memorabilia, relating to World War I.
Wreden, William P., collector.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical note
William P. Wreden was born in 1910 and died in 1995. He attended Stanford University and graduated in 1934. He owned and operated an antiquarian book business. In memory of his continued support of the Stanford Libraries, the University awards the Byra J. and William P. Wreden Prize for Collecting Books and Materials.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection is comprised of seventeen scrapbooks of newspaper clippings from the British press and memorabilia, relating to World War I. The scrapbooks contain articles pertaining to air raids in Europe, submarine attacks, naval battles, casualties, peace discussions and other topics.
World War, 1914-1918--Great Britain
- Volume I, 1914 August-September (Box-folder 1: 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes clippings on topics such as Britain's declaration of war on Germany, the British army in France, Germans nearing Paris, and wartime casualties.
- Volume II, 1914 September-October (Box-folder 1: 2)
  Includes topics such as zeppelin bombings, the surrender of Antwerp, and British naval victories.
- Volume III, 1914 October-November (Box-folder 1: 3)
  Topics include the first German attack on British coast, Britain's declaration of war on Turkey, and naval battles.
- Volume IV, 1914 November-December (Box-folder 2: 1)
  Includes articles on topics such as tension between nationalities, first air raids on English towns, and British retaliation air raids.
- Volume V, 1915 January 1-27 (Box-folder 2: 2)
- Volume VI, 1915 February 1-20 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  Includes articles on the Suez Canal, air raids in Belgium, and American blockades.
- Volume VII, 1915 February 6-March 24 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  Contains clippings of subjects including the increase in food prices, airplane raid in Essex, destruction of British ships, casualties, and peace terms.
- Volume VIII, 1915 March-May (Box-folder 3: 2)
  Includes articles written about torpedo attacks, zeppelin raids, German invasion of East Prussia, and the number of daily war casualties. Also contains a translation of the French newspaper, The Times, dedicated to the full text of diplomatic documents.
- Volume IX, 1915 May-July (Box-folder 3: 3)
  Includes stories regarding the sinking of the Lusitania by German submarines, the declaration of war by Italy, and the first zeppelin raid on London.
- Volume X, 1915 July-October (Box-folder 4: 1)
  Includes copy of the Daily Mail bird's-eye map of the British front. Clipping topics include German capture of Warsaw, zeppelin raids on the east coast, and the battle of Loos.
- Volume XI, 1915 October-1916 January (Box-folder 4: 2)
  Includes copy of the Daily Mail bird's-eye map of the front, section 2. Contains clippings relating to the Kitchener resignation, Lord Derby's letter, British casualties, and the fall of Cetinje.
- Volume XII, 1916 January-April (Box-folder 4: 3)
  Contains army prayer book. Also includes clippings regarding reduction in imports, German attack in Champagne, French withdrawl in Verdun, and rebellion in Ireland.
- Volume XIII, 1916 April-September (Box-folder 5: 1)
  Contains articles regarding the Irish rebellion, Verdun, and the Great naval battle off Horn's Reef.
- Volume XIV, 1916 September-1917 January (Box-folder 5: 2)
  Includes clippings about the sinking of a British hospital ship, daylight bombings of London, and the German call for a peace conference.
- Volume XV, 1917 January-June (Box-folder 5: 3)
  Includes clippings about a call for peace, food shortages, and military recruitment propaganda. Also includes examples of postcards from soldiers and various flag emblems attached to the back binding.
- Volume XVI, 1917 June-1918 July (Box-folder 6: 1)
  Clippings discuss an increased number of attacks, with both parties looking for an end to the war. Includes various ephemera and signage printed during the war.
- Volume XVII, 1918 July-November (Box-folder 6: 2)
  Includes memorial service and address by Bishop of London for fallen soldiers. Clippings discuss the end of the war and peace resolutions.